[music]
Welcome to Cypress Diaspora Uncovered.
This episode features an exclusive
fireside chat with one of the most
controversial [music] and compelling
figures in modern intelligence and
investigative journalism in conversation
with international business strategist
Philip Amaman. Former CIA
counterterrorism officer and
whistleblower John Kuryaku shares
extraordinary insights into national
[music] security, intelligence, ethics,
government accountability, and the
personal cost of exposing the truth.
This session [music] was recorded live
on the 8th of May 2026 at the Cypress
Diaspora Forum held at the Amara Hotel
in Limmerol, Cypress.
>> So ladies and gentlemen, uh good
afternoon and thank you for coming to
this uh fireside chat with John Kiryaku.
[music]
One of the uh amazing achievements that
uh Paul Lambis and his colleagues at the
Viaspora Forum have managed to do is
bring together talented people uh from
all walks of life, all parts of the
world. uh and we're lucky to have access
to them here uh over these you know two
or three days uh asking questions you
know learning there hearing from them
firsthand you know without a filter and
um as we saw earlier you know part of
these uh presentations are about
commerce part of them are about
technology law with John we have an
amazing opportunity to learn about
policy about forecasting about
intelligence about how decisions are
made at the global scale and um what the
situation looks like internally versus
what it looks like to the rest of us who
are getting our news from you know the
financial times or BBC or you know other
other sources of media. So we're very
fortunate that John is here. Thank you
very much for coming.
>> Thank you.
>> We appreciate your time. Um
>> happy to do it.
>> Uh for those of you who don't know uh
John was a uh intelligence uh operative
in both covert and overt uh departments.
So I should say in both intelligence and
uh operations
uh for a number of years. Um he
experienced both 911 and the uh entire
deployment to Afghanistan uh and Iraq
part of what is known today I guess as
the long war on terror or the global war
on terror. Uh after finishing his career
in the CIA where by the way he won
numerous intelligence awards he joined
the Senate. uh he he served as the
senior staffer to the Senate of the
United States of America. So going from
operations to uh the legislative branch,
which I think is an absolutely
fascinating progression. And um he's
also known as the CIA whistleblower
because he's one of the people with the
courage to publicly expose um some of
the events that were happening in the
global war on terror which were I would
say certainly counter to what we think
of as the Geneva Convention, the laws of
war and um other laws of operation as as
as we would like to to think of them. Um
so from being one of the most decorated
officers in the government he became
prosecuted by the government by the very
government that he served for a number
of years. Uh he spent 23 months in
prison. I think this was also almost a
graduate school of sorts or [laughter]
school
>> kind of was.
>> I've seen a number of your of your
podcasts on it which are just absolutely
fascinating.
And uh today he's a very prominent
commentator on public affairs, on
intelligence, uh on international
events. And um like I said, we're just,
you know, really really grateful that
he's here. And um I'd say that this is a
conversation among friends. Um you know,
we're not here to put anyone on the spot
or to, you know, maintain any kind of
political opinions or anything like
that, but to learn from each other. And
um I hope uh if we have some spare time
we'll also open up the questions from
the audience towards the end. [snorts]
So let's start. Uh John you've had this
incredible career both inside and
outside of government. And to us on the
outside who are you know in a way
consumers of government decisions and
consumers of public information. It
seems like the United States and the CIA
are these monolithic forces you know
where everything is planned. uh you know
everything has a certain scope and a
certain budget and a certain outcome. Uh
what's it like being on the inside and
uh how how difficult is it
>> watching a sausage being made?
>> Exactly. Yeah.
>> One of the things that I think most
people don't understand is that these
organizations that we're talking about,
the State Department, the Defense
Department, the CIA are big, slow,
lumbering bureaucracies.
But think of a bureaucracy that is
headed and staffed by people who think
they are smarter than everybody else in
the world. That they can't make a
mistake
while everybody's lying to them. And
intellectually they should know that
everybody's lying to them and they
don't. And I want to give you an
example.
After I left the CIA, I went to uh the
private sector to a firm called Deote.
one of the big four consulting firms and
then from Deote I went to work for
myself and Mccclardy who was Bill
Clinton's chief of staff took a liking
to me and offered me an office and a
part-time secretary was very generous.
Well, one of the other people who worked
in the office was Bill Richardson. Bill
had been the governor of New Mexico. He
had been a congressman. He was
ambassador to the United Nations. He was
the secretary of energy. Very serious
guy. and he had run for president. I
liked him so much I actually voted for
him after he dropped out of the race. I
just that's how much I liked him and
respected him. And he pulled me aside
oh the first week of January [sighs]
and he said, "Listen, I need to have a
private conversation with you." He said,
"I invited Obama to my house to watch
the Super Bowl, the big American
football, biggest game of the year." And
at halftime, they went for a walk on
Bill's ranch. Bill had like 1,200 acres
of just waste land, like nothing can
live there in the in the desert in New
Mexico. And he said at one point Obama
put his arm around his shoulder and
said, "Bill, if you endorse me and you
bring the Hispanic vote secretary of
state." And I said, "Hey, that's great."
And he says to me, "I want you to be my
deputy chief of staff." I said, "I'll
take it, but I want to be ambassador to
Greece or ambassador to Cyprus in the
second term." He said, "Done." I said,
"Great. Let's do it."
A year passes, almost a year, 11 months
pass, and Obama wins.
And the day after the election, Bill
came into the office and I said, "Mr.
Secretary, congratulations." He said,
"Oh my god, I'm so excited. I can't
believe I'm going to be Secretary of
State." I said, "We're going to do great
things. It's going to be so much fun."
Couple days later, I'm in the shower. I
have the news on on a radio in my
bathroom and I hear this news
announcement,
Hillary Clinton named Secretary of
State. And I thought, oh, oh, this is
bad. I go into the office.
And uh I said, "What happened?" He said,
"I don't know. I think he lied to me."
The next day, there's another
announcement. Bill Richardson named
Secretary of Commerce. I'm going to say
a bad word here, so I apologize in
advance. I go back into the office and I
said, ' Mr. Secretary, congratulations.
He says to me, "What the [__] do I know
about commerce?" [laughter]
Literally nothing. And I said, "No, no."
I said, "This is a good thing. There's
the Foreign Commercial Service. There's
the International Trade Representative.
We can make something out of this. And
then in the second term, you become
Secretary of State."
A couple of days later, he quit and just
withdrew. But then I get a call from
John Kerry. And Kerry says, "I'm going
to be the new chairman of the Senate
Foreign Relations Committee. I want you
to come to Capitol Hill and be the chief
investigator." I said, "Great. I'll I'll
do it, but I really do need the freedom
to investigate, you know, anything I
want. Anything that I think is
wrongdoing, I want to be able to
investigate it." He said, "Done." He was
a liar. Done. He says, "Done.
I investigated almost literally nothing
in the two and a half years I was
there." So,
one of the things about Carrie, to
answer your question, is like so many of
these these highle policy makers, they
think they're the smartest people in the
room or in the town. And Carrie had this
bad habit of going off script every time
he was in public. Everything is very
tightly scripted. Every single word that
he needs to say, it's on the paper which
is sitting in front of him. So he asks
me to go with him to the Brookings
Institution and we go there and he's
talking about I don't know what Yemen or
something. I don't know. I'm sitting in
the first seat and he says he goes off
script. I have the script in my hand.
I'm I'm reading along with him and he
says, "You know,
I invited Obama to my house for
Christmas two years ago and after
Christmas dinner, we were walking around
and I'm looking at him like
it's not on the script." He says, "We
were walking around after dinner and
Obama put his arm around my shoulder and
he said, "Bill, I mean that John." He
says,
If you endorse me before the Kennedys
do, Secretary of State [laughter]
and I I start going like this
and he's looking at me and then he just
continues with the story that he got he
got robbed.
And afterwards I said, "Senator, you you
can't tell that story in public. Not if
you ever hope to become Secretary of
State." I said, "Richardson tells
exactly the same story." And as it
turned out, so did so did uh Eric
Holder. Eric Holder was supposed to be
the secretary of state. He ended up
being the attorney general. He promised
it to six people. We were able to figure
out he promised secretary of state. If
you do this, you do that, you endorse
me, you bring this this group of people,
you bring that group of people,
secretary of state. But the thing is is
they all think they're so smart
that their conclusion is, of course, he
would make me secretary of state. I'm me
of any president would make me secretary
of state because I'm so smart. Well, the
thing is is if you put all these smart
people in a room and they're at the
policym level, everybody beneath them is
going to be too afraid to say anything.
If you have all these smart people who
are midlevel or lower level, they engage
in group think.
>> Yeah. and the and with group think they
almost always get it wrong. So I learned
very quickly that these really smart,
really important people really aren't so
smart and then after a while they're
really not so important either. At the
CIA I saw a group think with disastrous
consequences.
Um, do the Iraqis have weapons of mass
destruction?
Of course they didn't. We all knew they
didn't. There was literally no
intelligence, literally zero
intelligence that the Iraqis had weapons
of mass destruction. And Condisa Rice
told George Tennant, "You're going to go
to the UN and you're going to say that
there are weapons of mass destruction."
President Bush, God bless President
Bush, he was just a stupid person.
When he asked George directly, "Are
there weapons of mass destruction?"
George said, "Mr. President, it's a slam
dunk." Yeah,
>> he knew that that wasn't true, but he
knew that Dick Cheney really, really
wanted there to be weapons of mass
destruction.
So, we wrote this paper for him and we
said the Iraqis had a nuclear program
that they disbanded in 1985.
Right? There were UN weapons
inspections. There's no zero evidence of
a nuclear weapons program. There is no
evidence of an intercontinental
ballistic missile program. We found the
shells of the of the ICBMs in the desert
and they had been buried there since the
late 1980s.
Biological weapons. [snorts]
You can make a biological weapon in your
kitchen if you really wanted to. It's
impossible to determine if a country has
a biological weapons program or not.
Chemical weapons.
The Iraqis used chemicals on their own
people. The Shia Muslims in the south
and the Kurds in the north. But they did
away with the program in 1991 when the
UN weapons inspections uh began taking
place. So George knew that there were no
weapons of mass destruction. And then he
went to the UN with John Negropanti and
Colin Powell and they said there are
weapons of mass destruction and that's
the reason we're going to war. Well then
the Washington Post had a front page
article saying they're lying.
George Tennant lied to the to the face
of the president of the United States
when he said it was a slam dunk and
George complained to Condisa Rice and he
said this isn't fair because I told you
that there were no weapons and you told
me that I had to say there were weapons.
I had never seen George this angry ever.
Condisa Rice told him her exact words.
George, you're just going to have to
take one for the team.
That's what happens when you engage in
this group think in a giant bureaucracy
where everybody thinks he's smarter than
everybody else.
>> So, I'm I'm getting two lessons from
this. First of all, that Netflix series
seems to be eerily accurate. [laughter]
>> Yeah. And and so is the movie Vice.
>> Yeah.
>> Check it out.
>> Yeah. Yeah. But the second thing is it
seems, you know, my my next question was
going to be about George Tennet and all
of the reforms that took place in the
wake of 9/11. Um
>> Yeah. And yet we find ourselves again
today um in a war in the Middle East. Um
and it's not clear what the reasons for
that are. It's not clear if there was an
intelligence case or if there was, you
know, how the decision was made. Um
>> I can tell you exactly how the decision
>> Oh, we'd love to hear, please.
[sighs and gasps]
Beginning in 1986,
when Ronald Reagan was president,
Israeli prime ministers began asking on
every one of their visits to the White
House for the United States to bomb
Iran. It didn't matter who the who the
president was. It didn't matter who the
Israeli prime minister was. Please bomb
Iran. Please bomb Iran. Please bomb
Iran. Reagan said no. George HW Bush
said no. Bill Clinton said no. George W.
Bush said no. Obama.
>> Barack Obama said no. Donald Trump said
no in his first term.
We just learned two weeks ago that not
only did Joe Biden say no, but when he
was vice president under Obama,
Netanyahu, Benjamin Netanyahu, the prime
minister of Israel, said, "If you don't
bomb Iran, we're going to use nuclear
weapons." And Obama said, "Go ahead. Go
ahead. Use them. You feel that
threatened, go ahead and use them. We're
not gonna stop you.
>> He called the blood.
>> Basically,
>> Netanyahu has made 11 trips to the
United States in the last 18 months and
he finally convinced Trump to do it. The
the word that I've heard from friends at
the White House is that he told Trump
like he told Obama, "I'm going to use
nuclear weapons." And so to save the
Iranian people,
Trump elected to start bombing Iran. And
then we find ourselves in a war with no
end. May I draw a parallel,
>> please?
>> I've told this story before, but it
bears repeating. I think it's on point.
The night before we invaded Iraq,
uh we we had something called a
principles committee meeting. The
principles committee like it sounds,
it's chaired by the president and the
attendees are the vice president and his
top people and a notetaker. The
secretary of state and his noteaker, the
secretary of defense and his notetaker,
the chairman and joint chairman of the
chiefs of staff and their notetaker, the
director of the CIA and his notetaker.
And so we're going to go in in 12 hours.
This is our final meeting.
The briefer was the commander of central
command, General Tommy Franks. I never
liked General Franks. He had a filthy
mouth and it was one of these guys who
thought he was smarter than everybody
else. He four shiny stars on his
shoulder,
swearing every other word. And um
for whatever reason, and I don't
remember the reason, the president
wasn't there. So the vice president uh
chaired the meeting and I was sitting
George Tennant is sitting like this at
our conference room table and there's a
microphone right here. I'm sitting
directly behind him taking notes and um
Vice President Cheney asks General
Franks to give the what's called the
order of battle briefing. And I've
mentioned before I always hated or order
Order of Battle briefings. They're so
boring. and they they open a map and
they're like elements of the ninth
mountain division or 20 kilometers like
I don't care where the little men are on
the map. It doesn't matter to me at all
and they're going to move in 15 minutes
anyway. So he finished this briefing and
as he's finishing he says if all goes as
planned we'll be in Tehran by August.
And very discreetly, George turns off
his microphone and he says, "Did he say
Baghdad or did he say Thran?"
And I said, "He said Thran."
And George says, "Have these people lost
their minds?" And then he turns the
microphone back on and just finishes,
you know, the meeting like that. As we
were getting up, one of the National
Security Council officials said, "When
we cross that border tomorrow morning,
they're going to throw flowers at us."
And I went back to the I was the
executive assistant to the deputy
director at the time. I went back to the
deputy director's office. He said, "How
was the principal committee meeting?" I
said, "Did you know we were going to
invade Iran?"
And he said, "Are they still talking
about that we're not going to invade
Iran?" And I said, "Do these people know
nothing about history?" And he said, 'N
no, they know nothing about history, but
they're leading our country.
And so once the policy is made, the
policy is made. When I got back from
Pakistan, I had I had been the chief of
CIA uh counterterrorism operations in
Pakistan from January to May of 2002. So
just as 9/11
uh the fallout from 911 was settling and
um
[sighs]
and I went back to headquarters and I
got promoted because of my work in
Pakistan and the deputy director chose
me as his assistant. So I walked in on
the first day and I said, "So I
said,"What are we doing?" And he said,
"Actually, I can't tell you. You have to
go to security and sign a bunch of
secrecy agreements and then I'll tell
you what we're doing." I said, "Okay,
well that's weird, but okay." So I went
up to security and they had six secrecy
agreements sitting out waiting for me to
sign them. So I signed each one and I
said to the guy, I knew the guy, I said,
"So what's up? what's the big secret?
And he says, "Well,
next year we're going to invade Iraq.
We're going to overthrow Saddam Hussein
and we're going to open the world's
largest air force base. And then we're
going to move all of our air assets out
of Saudi Arabia so that we can deprive
Osama bin Laden of the ability to say
that we've polluted the land of the two
holy mosques."
And I was dumbfounded.
I had just gotten back from Pakistan
like two days earlier.
And I said to him, "But we haven't
caught Bin Laden yet." And the whole
point of that so-called, and I hate the
name, global war on terror. The whole
point was to capture or kill Osama bin
Laden. And he put up his hands. He says,
"Listen, the decision's already been
made. There's no more discussion, but
the battle lines are drawn." He said the
the pro-war forces are the office of the
vice president OBVP OSD the office of
the secretary of defense
and the national security council and
the anti-war listen to how crazy this is
the anti-war faction was the CIA the
state department and the joint chiefs of
staff he said the decision's been made
we have to do as we're told and so it
took us like nine more months
10 more months and then we invaded Iraq
and we're bogged down for the next what
17 years.
>> Yeah.
>> So we've gone from an era where we have
you know national technical means we
have humans uh sigans all of these you
know different formats to today when
we're really looking at big data we're
looking at artificial intelligence we're
looking at a
>> a very very different environment. Um
uh and yet it seems as if the human in
the loop decisionm you know if if that's
not fixed at a systemic level
>> make the same
>> this is a very important point
>> you know with with the quickness the
rapidity with which technology develops
>> there's this almost knee-jerk desire to
just rely on the technology after 911
George Tennant got special congressional
approval
to use taxpayer funds to begin investing
in tech startups. Crazy, right?
>> That was reported the CIA incubator.
>> It's called Inqel.
>> Yeah.
>> Um they thought they were cute. They
took the word Intel and then put the
letter Q in the middle as a nod to James
Bond to to Q from the James Bond movies.
Um Q was always in charge of tech. So
the very first uh investment they made
and I think it was
I think it was a million and a half
dollars was to um
oh what's his name? Peter Teal. What's
was his company?
>> Palanteer. Thank you. Palunteer which is
now a multi-billion dollar concern
>> and a huge public contractor. Right.
>> Huge giant public sector contractor. I
mean, it it's got it's screaming in neon
conflict of interest, you know, but they
did it anyway.
>> And uh and it's not just Palanteer. It's
it's dozens and dozens of very high-tech
companies. The CIA was in up to its neck
on AI,
but
you can't have a successful intelligence
operation
without a human being. You just can't.
You need somebody that is inside the
room when the plans are being made
because Palanteer is not going to
collect the information. And it's not
like Saddam Hussein's going to be on the
phone saying, "Listen, our plans for the
uh next attack are, "Do you have a pen?"
You know, that just doesn't
>> take down these coordinates.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. That just doesn't
happen. You have to have a human being
inside the room.
>> Um
>> Excuse me. Let me add one more thought.
Go ahead. Besides the fact that in this
era of AI and um and uh facial
recognition software,
>> it makes it that much harder for CIA
officers to cross borders, right? And so
you have to be able to affect an
operation that doesn't cross borders.
And the only way you can do that is to
recruit a human being to give you the
information.
Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. Um, as we look at technology, uh,
you know, we're not looking only at
intelligence decision-m,
but we're looking at, um, electoral
decision-m and electoral outcomes. And
I, we saw with the Obama election, uh,
the whole, um, you know, the Facebook AB
testing,
>> uh, thing, which was very beneficial for
Obama. We saw the Cambridge scandal
scandals
>> prior to that. This time around we had
Elon Musk paying in nearly 300 million
to support the election in seven
battleground states. As we move forward
is universal suffrage and I know this is
a controversial question but as we move
forward I mean can we have free and fair
elections if the technological landscape
is so open to manipulation?
>> I want so badly to say yes and I'm not
sure that I can. Yeah.
>> You know, and here's getting back to the
so many people are so stupid theme.
All anybody wants to talk about in the
United States, at least among the
Democrats, and I am I am an independent
independent.
I really am. I I was a I was a third
generation Democrat and I left the
Democratic party because it moved too
far to the right
um on foreign policy.
So,
what they want to talk about in the
United States is that the Russians,
>> you know, the Russians uh interfered in
the election. Well, you know, let's look
at that. The Russians spent $50,000 on
Facebook ads. They spent half of the
50,000 after the election was over. So,
they spent 25,000. Almost every dollar
of it was spent in states that were
either solidly Hillary Clinton or
solidly Donald Trump. So, we're supposed
to believe that it was the Russians that
threw the election. We're not supposed
to believe that it was Elon Musk who put
in $300 million of his own money or um
uh the the guy from Las Vegas that owns
all the casinos.
Sheldon Adlesen who spent 150 million of
his own money to the Trump super PAC or
his wife. Sheldon Adlesen died recently.
His wife put in another hundred million
of her money. We have this absolutely
terrible Supreme Court decision in the
United States called Citizens United.
Citizens United made a decision during
the Obama administration that
corporations are people.
They literally said that in the decision
corporations are people and as people
corpor corporations can donate as much
money as they want to American
elections.
Well, we had a $2,000 limit if you're a
human being. No limit if you're donating
to a political action committee. So,
what you do is you just create your own
political action committee and put $500
million on it and then spend it all on
one candidate
and that's democracy. So, I wish I could
say yes in answer to your question, but
I I genuinely
fear
for the political future of the United
States, which is why I'm buying an
apartment in Greece this year.
>> Excellent. [laughter]
>> Well, if the Greek political system has
become superior to the American one, I
think Houston, we have a problem.
>> You know what? The Greeks though, the
Greeks do something that I really like
and it's very simple. [snorts]
>> They don't allow any campaigning. The
the elections are always on Sunday.
Yeah. They don't allow any campaigning
past I think it's Thursday before.
>> Yeah.
>> And no polls are permitted to be uh
reported on or released publicly.
>> Yes.
>> I like it. It's like a cooling cooling
off period.
>> Yeah. No, I I I I joke about the Greek
political system, but the elections are
actually very efficient. Uh they you
know, polling opens in the morning, it
closes, it's monitored by members of the
bar,
>> and the result is known. It's a
paperbased count, and the result is
known that same evening. I voted in my
grandfather's
secondary school,
>> okay,
>> in our ancestral village in 2019. I had
never voted in Greece before. I flew to
Greece just to vote. And um they give
you this stack of paper like this big.
It was 36 squares of paper and each
paper had the name of the party, the
logo of the party, and a picture of the
leader of the party. So if you're, you
know, you can't read, you can still
vote. I had no idea that there were six
communist parties in Greece.
>> Yes. [laughter]
And they were unreconstructed communist
parties.
>> Unreonstructed. And they all hate each
other.
>> That's right. That's right.
>> So I'm leafing through all the communist
parties. And then there are four or five
fascist parties and neo-Nazi parties.
And then you get to the ones in the
middle. You just pick the one that you
like and you put it in an envelope and
seal it. You come out of the booth, the
voting booth. You throw away the 35
pages that you didn't use. There's a big
barrel of garbage. You throw it in there
and then you put your vote in the box.
It's perfectly
>> Yeah.
>> logical and easy. And
>> it is. And you show your ID. Everyone
has an ID. There's no
>> You show your ID. They cross your name
off the list. You're good to go.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> You've spent the past week uh here in
Cyprus, um including a visit to
Nicariah. Mhm.
>> How how how do you feel seeing, you
know, the divided capital and the the
green line and the
>> I'll tell you the honest to God's truth.
So I got here kind of late in the in the
day and I drove up from uh Larnica. So
it was dark by the time I got there and
I checked into the hotel. I went out
onto the balcony. I called my friend to
tell her I had arrived in Nicicoia and I
look up and I said, "What the [__] is
that?" She said, "What?" I said,
"There's a giant crescent in lights
crescent moon on the side of the
mountain."
>> Yeah.
>> She's like, "Oh, yeah. They've been
doing that like in our face for many
years now. I do not remember that when I
was here in 1992." And she said, "No,
they lit it up later on after 1992.
On principle, I had never been to the
occupied side. I I refused. But then I
had a meeting on Monday with the mayor
of Nicicoia and he urged me to go. So I
went I was there for 45 minutes and I
told my friend I feel like I have to
take a shower. I can't do this anymore.
[applause]
So I I walked back.
Although I will tell you, I I talked to
a lot of people this week, professors
and lawyers and activists and political
figures, and every single person I
talked to had nothing but nice things to
say about Turkish criates. It's the
Turkish occupiers and the settlers that
are the problem.
And [applause] yeah,
if I don't want to put you on the spot,
but if you had to make a forecast of how
this situation might be solved, can it
be solved?
Just, you know, looking at this as an
outsider
objective opinion, independent opinion,
what do you think?
>> Three weeks ago, I I had dinner, don't
yell at me, I had dinner with the
Turkish foreign deputy foreign minister.
He was in Washington. He read an article
that I wrote about Syria and he invited
me to dinner.
So I thought, "Ah, what the heck? It'll
be my chance to get a couple of points
across." So we got to this really nice
Italian restaurant and um and he said,
"So I wanted to talk about Syria." I
said, "Yeah, we can talk about Syria all
you want, but you have to get out of
Cypress." And he laughs. He says, "No,
but seriously, you know this situation
in Syria." I said, "I appreciate it, but
you have to get out of Cypress." And
finally he said, "Okay, noted,
[laughter]
but I really want to talk about Syria."
So we talked about Syria for most of the
dinner. And at the end I said, "What are
the prospects for getting out of
Cyprus?"
And he said, "It's not going to happen.
It's just not going to happen. It's like
telling the Israelis to get out of the
West Bank. We all know they should. We
all want them out, but they're not going
anywhere." And especially because, you
know, this is what makes foreign affairs
so complicated and it's one of the
things that I love about it.
Um,
you've got the Israelis that used to be
practically joined at the hip with the
Turks, right? When I was younger and I
was going to Greece as a tourist or to
see family, um, the Greeks were very,
very close to the Palestinians and very
close really to all the Arab countries.
>> Yeah. Um and um and then it flipped when
Erdogan decided he didn't like the
Israelis anymore.
Then the Greeks flipped and the Greeks
said, "Well, you know, as they say in
the Middle East, the enemy of my enemy
is my friend." And all all of a sudden
they've got this relationship and then
they found natural gas under the water
here in Cyprus. And the next thing you
know, these very strange alliances are
forming.
I had a meeting a week ago Tuesday with
a senator, a Republican senator. He's a
committee chairman.
And I said, "Senator, I got to ask you a
question." I said, "Friends of mine have
been asking me this rhetorical question.
The Turks and the Israelis hate each
other, and their language has become
increasingly belligerent over the last
several months.
And so
the Israeli deputy foreign minister said
that Israel's next big fight is going to
be against the Turks.
Well, if the Turks invoke Article 5 of
the NATO charter, the Americans and the
rest of NATO are going to have to attack
Israel.
Can you imagine such a thing? That will
never ever happen. Of course, that would
be the death of NATO. But on paper,
that's the way it's supposed to work
out. An attack on one is an attack on
all. I said, 'What do you think about
that?
He said, 'You don't seriously think that
it was an accident that the president of
Cyprus talked yesterday about a European
Union military alliance. And I said,
"No, of course not, because NATO is
going to going to die
and the Europeans have to protect
themselves because they can't trust the
United States to protect them."
I think that's all what it comes down
to. I I think the Turks are in the
catbird seat. They know that the status
quo benefits them. It doesn't cost them
anything other than money, you know, for
settlers.
And the longer they're there, the more
de facto
becomes,
you know, dour.
>> Yes. Yeah. Especially with the
demographic change and the
>> especially with the demographic change
which is the most danger dangerous
component here.
>> Okay.
>> These are Anatolians we're talking
about. They're not criates. They're not
ethnic criates.
>> Yeah. And also the original population
in 1974 which had to to move is is very
old now. So
>> the memories of a of a real you know by
communal population are are are rapidly
disappearing. I said to the mayor the
other day, when the Turkish criates or
even more precisely when the Turks who
are settlers look across the line and
see the success, the economic success
that is Cyprus,
they have to be jealous, right? I mean,
they have to be having a conversation
like, you know, why can't we have a
piece of that? Why do we allow ourselves
to be divided?
And he said, I don't think they have
that conversation.
He said that the the Turks give them
whatever they need, free land that they
stole from the criates,
from the Greek criates, and uh you know,
why upset the apple cart?
Yeah.
Moving on to uh Cypress and
international events. So Cypress has had
very close relations with Russia since
uh the USSR fell apart and um we've
traditionally had very very close
relationships with the Gulf.
>> Yeah.
>> And we we now see active conflicts in
both of these areas um with the 2014
invasion of Crimea. There was the
embargo that had a a big domino effect
here in Cypress and that a lot of uh
Russian bank accounts were closed,
Russian companies had to close and so on
and so forth. And so there's a good deal
of expectation, you know, when we look
at the conflict in Ukraine, you know,
it's it's not merely an academic
concern. How is this going to end?
Because uh we have a large Russian
population in Cyprus. We have mixed
families. We have children. You know,
it's it's not just
>> something theoretical. It's something
actually very very real.
>> Your forecast again, you've got 30 plus
years of experience with conflicts. How
do you see that ending?
>> Yeah. The Russia Ukraine one is is
tough.
Um,
three or four years ago, the Russian
ambassador invited me to lunch one day
with six other independent journalists.
We had all written about the conflict
and he wanted to
dig a little deeper. And one of the
questions, the most important question
he asked me was how
or he said, "Was it possible for the
United States and Russia to have some
sort of diplomatic cooperation even in a
time of war? Was there anything that the
two countries could do that we used to
call confidence building measures
just to try to stop the relationship
from going down the drain that it was
then circling?" And I said, 'Yes,
counterterrorism, counterp
proliferation, and counter narcotics,
we can always always cooperate on those
issues whether there is war or not.
And I said, but I will add one thing.
I said, 'When when when you arrest
a black woman basketball player because
she has just the smallest amount of
marijuana oil
in her, you know, toiletries kit and you
give her 10 years at hard labor,
you lose the support of the American
people. It's a bad look." He was furious
and he said, "Do you have any idea how
many American how many Russians are in
American prisons?" because I do. He said
1,500. What about them? And I said, "By
all means, trade them. Certainly, you
can agree on that. The the United States
doesn't want its prisoners in Russian
prisons, and the Russians don't want
their prisoners in American prisons.
Just trade them." And that would be good
because you would be talking, at least
talk to one another. Here we are three,
four years later and for all intents and
purposes, the Ukrainians have lost. Uh
it's certainly possible for the
Ukrainians to make a couple of inroads
in these occupied areas now. Donets,
Donetsk, Luhansk, Crimea. Um they likely
won't. And to tell you the truth, the
United States is not committed to
Ukraine anymore. It's just not. that was
very much a Democratic Party foreign
policy issue. The Republicans are not at
all interested.
On the other hand, if the Russians
suddenly found themselves in trouble on
the ground, they can turn to the North
Koreans or the Chinese or African
mercenaries and just offer up an endless
supply of of fighters. The Ukrainians
can't do that. And then on the other
hand too, the third hand, if there is
such a thing, um the Europeans are
staunchly in the corner of the
Ukrainians, but they can't send troops
because they're all NATO members. And if
NATO were to be involved officially,
that upgrades the level of the conflict.
>> Yeah. I want to challenge you a bit on
the Ukrainian side because um
>> they've done remarkably well in in
stabilizing the battle lines um in in
forming a a series of defensive
positions in drone warfare and you know
a number of areas.
>> Um I'm sophisticated in drone warfare.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And that's in the face of a
lot of attacks on civilian
infrastructure.
>> Absolutely right.
>> You know heating infrastructure. So, I
mean, it's uh I uh I think the whole
world is in a way astounded at how
they've they've been able to defend
themselves.
>> I'm I'm astounded. I think it's very
brave what they've done. They've been
able to hold off one of the biggest
armies in the world, but
>> they just don't have enough
>> to reclaim
>> to break through. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. I I think in the end it's going to
be how you define
>> win. I think in the end, like many
people predicted at the very start of
this conflict, the Ukrainians are going
to have to give up some territory.
They're not going to be able to reclaim
some territory.
>> But it may also just be a frozen
conflict where there's no decision on
the termistice,
whatever, North Korea, South Korea type
thing.
>> Absolutely. Yes.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So, no prospects of a
normalization, I guess. You know, I I
hate to say I I've long been accused of
being um overly optimistic,
and this is one of those rare
areas where I'm I'm not optimistic. I'm
not optimistic about Palestine is
another one.
>> Yes. Yeah.
>> I'm just not.
>> Yeah. The recent events were really
shocking.
>> It's been so terrible. And you know,
we've got these we've got these
evangelical Christians in the United
States that are irrational. You know,
sometimes I do a lot of podcasts, like a
lot. And sometimes I'm just in a bad
mood, right? And so I'll say things just
because I'm in a bad mood and I'll just
let out a zinger. And I said recently,
and I took all kinds of guff for it. I
said, ' Listen, if your religion was
founded in 1880 in somebody's basement,
it's a cult. [laughter]
You can call it evangelical Christianity
if you want. It's a cult. [laughter]
And I took a lot of [__] for that.
>> I can imagine.
>> But the truth is, [laughter]
the truth is it's the evangelicals that
are blindly pro-Israel.
And the end result is the decimation of
the oldest Christian community in the
world.
Nobody cares about Palestine's
Christians.
Why? If you're so Christian that you
speak in tongues and God speaks back to
you and you have conversations with him,
then why are you abetting in the murder
of Christians?
I just simply don't understand it.
>> Yeah. Well, there's a lot of
contradictions for sure.
[sighs and gasps] And uh looking at
Iran, I was tweeting again this morning.
I mean, it's a mystery for me that uh
President Trump says, "We've defeated
the Iranian army."
>> He he tweeted it yesterday. It's all
over. We won.
>> I think that's the fifth or sixth time
he tweeted that same thing.
>> At the same time, I was reading the FT
this morning that Iran actually attacked
Dubai again yesterday. They've attacked
the ships that tried to get come out.
>> Yeah.
>> I mean, what's what's going on? There
seems a total disconnect between, you
know, standard decision-m, rational
decision-m
>> Benjamin Netanyahu told him that the
Iranian government would collapse when
the first missile was fired.
>> Got it. Got it. A chalabe. That's an
Ahmed Chalabi.
>> It's an Ahmed Chalabby moment. Yes.
>> Um,
>> every analyst in Washington knew that
wasn't true. We had been saying it for
the last 45 years.
Yes, the regime is unpopular. Yes,
people hate the IRGC, but Hillary
Clinton's I I hate Hillary Clinton and I
hate quoting her, but she was right
about one thing. She said, "Iran is not
a theocracy. It's a military
dictatorship and it's run by the IRGC."
And that's true. And it's heavy and it's
ownorous and you'll end up hanging from
a a street light if you if you look at
them the wrong way. I get it. But it's
the same situation with Iraq in 2003.
Why did the Iraqis not throw flowers at
us? Because we're not seen as
liberators. We're seen as invaders and
occupiers who will invade and occupy for
decades.
And they would rather have the devil
they know than the devil they don't.
Plain and simple.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. Um maybe moving forward. Maybe
[gasps] looking forward say the next 5
years 10 years what do you think are the
main um I guess the main trends or the I
don't want to say threats because
they're also opportunities but you know
the people in this room are all
businessmen entrepreneurs startupers
it's you know we we are and and we're
all we're in a tiny economy which is
kind of very exposed to these trends
>> right
>> what what should we what should be on
our radar screen like top three top
three issues in your opinion
>> political division vision.
>> Yep.
>> Right. In the United States, it started
in earnest in uh in 1994
and the pendulum hasn't swung back yet.
>> Um
we've gotten to the point where
well yesterday um yesterday a woman sent
me an email saying that we've been
Facebook friends. I've never met her.
I've never met 90% of my Facebook
friends, but she said, "We've been
Facebook friends for whatever
18 years or whatever, and she's blocking
me."
>> She's blocking me because I um I speak
to Tucker Carlson.
>> Yeah. Bad man. Very bad.
>> Yeah.
>> Very, very bad.
>> And I said, "Okay,
I will not engage in political purity
tests."
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, yeah. I'll give you a better a
better [laughter] story. So, I'm
divorced and um once I finally got over
my divorce, I decided I'm going to check
out these apps, right? These dating
apps. So, uh so I see this woman. I
said, "Oh my god, this woman's so
beautiful." I swipe right. She swipes
right. I said, "Hey, great." We start
texting each other. We arranged to go
out for a drink.
Even more beautiful than the pictures.
And I said to her, because I'm totally
transparent, I said, "Listen,
I'm having fun. I'd love to see you
again, but there's something you should
know about me, and if you don't like it,
you can walk and no hard feelings." She
says, "Oh, I know who you are, Mr.
Kiryaku." And I hadn't told her my last
name. I said, "Oh, okay. So, you're okay
with that?" And she said, "Yes, you
should know something about me. I'm the
deputy assistant secretary of state for
human rights."
And I said, "We're a match."
>> Great.
>> Wait, wait. Under whose administration?
>> Uh, by
>> Okay.
>> So, I said, "This is great." More than
that, she had a master's degree in
archaeology and did a dig in Greece for
her for her master's degree. So, we're
talking about Greece and she spoke some
Greek and it was great. So, we go out
for a second date. Had a fantastic time.
And I said, "Hey, let me take you to
Shepherd'stown, West Virginia on
Saturday. I've always wanted to see it.
It's an hour and 15 minutes away from
from Washington, old Civil War town.
They have galleries and boutiques and
stuff." She said, "Great." I said, "I'll
pick you up at 10:00." So, I go to her
house. I pick her up at 10:00. She gets
in the car. I said, "Good morning." She
goes, "Hello."
I was like, "Dog gone it."
>> You must have said something.
>> I said, "What's wrong?" Nothing.
[laughter]
It's like every time. And I said,
"Obviously something is wrong. What is
wrong?" And she says, "I saw a YouTube
video last night of you quoting Ronald
Reagan."
[snorts] And I said, "Oh, I know what
you're talking about. I stand by that
quote." I said, "Ronald Reagan was right
when he said that government is the
problem. It's not the solution to the
problem."
you told that into a Democratic deputy
assistant.
>> And she goes, I I just need to process
this. I have serious doubts about your
left-wing credentials, she said. I said,
excuse me. I went to prison for my
leftwing credentials. So, silence all
the way to West Virginia. So, we walk
around and I'm telling her, look, you
know, it's it's important to be
independent. It's important to think for
yourself. What's happened to our country
since the 1990s, there's no going back
from it. We all hate each other.
Families are split. Friendships are
ending. For what? For politics. Because
you don't like my position on abortion.
You're never going to speak to me again.
It's ridiculous. So, she I got her calm
down. 3:00 it starts to rain like really
hard. I said, "Why don't we head back to
Washington?" So, we get in my car. I
don't like sitting on my phone in the
car. So, I take my phone out. I put it
in the cup holder right here. And just
as I start to drive, the phone goes
text message. So I look and I thought,
[__] [laughter]
it's from Tucker Carlson and it says it
says, "Hey buddy, haven't heard from you
in a while. [laughter] Are you free for
a beer?" It's like, "Dang it." So I look
like I'm looking at her like this like
trying not to. And she's looking right
at the phone. [laughter]
Dog gone it. And then she says, "Do you
know Tucker Carlson?" [laughter] And I
said, "Yes, and he's a lovely man.
And she said, "Take me home right now
and don't ever call me again."
>> That's America. That's America today.
That is America today. So, number one,
we all hate each other for stupid,
meaningless reasons.
>> Got it. Got it.
>> Yeah.
>> Number two,
since the mid 1990s, there has been no
consistency in American foreign policy.
We used to have this phrase, I'm sure
you remember it, that our differences on
foreign policy ended at the shore.
>> Yeah.
>> And now
we got the vice president threatening
the pope and we're saying we're going to
use nuclear weapons on this guy and
we're threatening to invade Greenland
and uh everybody's gone insane. Yeah.
>> And then the next guy's going to come in
and he's going to try to fix things, but
he's going to go too far maybe on the
other side and then the Republicans are
going to come back in and it's a
disaster. But it's a disaster that most
Americans don't understand the import of
travel constantly, right? All around the
world, mostly to the Gulf and to Europe.
And in Europe, they're genuinely worried
like, "We don't want we don't know what
to make of you guys anymore." I was I
had a meeting with an MI6, a guy at at
the British MI6 that I used to work with
when I was at the CIA, and we went out
for a for a coffee when I was last
there.
And he said, "It did start in the mid
'9s, but it really took off after 9/11."
He said, "We always used to have fun
with you guys, but then you just started
murdering everybody. Everybody whose
politics you don't like, you just murder
them. Whether it's close in with the
little team or you drop a bomb or you
fire a missile, you can't kill
everybody. I said, "Oh my god, I say
that about the Israelis all the time.
You can't have a policy to just kill
everybody. That's the policy. And then
you can develop their land after you've
killed them all." But that's the split
that we face in the United States right
now. And it makes Europe weaker. And it
makes the Gulf weaker. I was in Kuwait,
I don't know, six or eight weeks ago,
and Kuwait is in a state of chaos right
now. Nobody's reporting on it because
nobody really cares. It's not Dubai or
Abu Dhabi or even Qatar. But um but in
Kuwait, they're panicked. Look at that
neighborhood. They have Iran on the one
side, they have Iraq on the north, they
have the Saudis whom they hate on the
west, and the Americans are preoccupied
with, you know, invading Greenland. And
so they're panicked about what this
means for them.
>> But is the next guy going to be any
better?
>> Who is the next guy? We don't even know.
I went on Cali the other day. It's one
of these predictive apps.
And you can bet on, you know, who's
going to be the Democratic nominee for
president or the Republican nominee.
There are 44 people for the Democrats
and 24 people for the Republicans. We
don't even know who's going to lead our
country in two years.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. So, uh, political division,
>> lack of consistency, the systems
breaking down.
>> Yeah. And, and another one is is
economic uncertainty.
>> Yeah.
>> You know, the constitution could not
possibly be any clearer. The president
cannot put tariffs on a country. Can't.
Illegal. Can't do it. And then Trump
says 100% tariffs on everybody. And
Congress said, "Oh my god, what are we
going to do? What are we going to do?
You're the only ones who can put
tariffs."
Say, "No, no tariffs. We have to do the
tariffs. You can come to us with your
ideas and we'll put the tariffs."
Instead, there are tariffs for a year
while it worked its way through the
courts. And the courts said, you know,
in the Constitution, it says the
president can't do this. So, it's led to
this economic uncertainty. And not just
at that basic level of of tariffs, look
at energy and renewable energy. We were
making great strides in renewable
energy. you know,
solar panels all over the the California
desert, all over Texas to the point
where in a handful of states, a majority
of our electricity was coming from
either wind or solar. And then even on
the on the East Coast from tidal power,
which is amazing.
>> And then Trump said, "No, we're not
doing any of that anymore." I I drive
through Pennsylvania a lot. It's my home
state. And um I I noticed on the
Pennsylvania Turnpike now there are big
billboards
that say the sun sets, winds die, coal
is forever. It's like coal.
It's not the 19th century anymore.
But that's the position of a whole lot
of people in the United States.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Okay. Why don't we open up
to some questions from the audience? I
think uh
>> that sounds good. I think it would be
really really cool to hear some
questions. Let's start over here.
[laughter]
>> Only ju only just recently did I did I
come to understand it. I went to Dubai
and my niece called me and she says Theo
John you're exploding on TikTok. I said
why? [laughter] She said I have no idea.
And I said okay. And then I went to bed.
And the next morning I got a call. I got
a call from the biggest talent agency in
the world. And this guy says to me, I'm
an agent with you know so and so. He
says tell me you're not represented.
>> [laughter]
>> I said no I'm not not represented. He
said you are now.
>> I said okay the biggest talent agency in
the world.
>> So they connect me with different
partners.
One for Hollywood scripted, Hollywood
unscripted
literary
podcasting
uh licensing which I didn't even realize
was a thing.
and uh and speak speaking.
So, I thought, "Wow, they're rolling out
the red carpet." And then the uh
the literary agent, he was he was he's
older than I am, and it never smiled.
Everybody else was all smiles and
laughing and oh, we're going to do this
and we're going to do that. And he's
just kind of sitting there. And then the
lead partner said, "I want to introduce
you to your new literary agent. This is
Sloan Harris." And I said, "Sloan
Harris, I know you." And he said, "Have
we met?" And I said, "No, you're Stephen
King's literary agent." And he said,
"Oh, yeah. Stephen and I go back 35
years." And he says, "And I represent
James Patterson and I represent Steven
Flynn and I represent Dr. Seuss and
James or uh sorry, Jane Mayor."
And I said, "My god, they're giants."
and he said, "And now you and I'm not
taking any more clients." And that's
when I started thinking, "Oh, this is
for real. It's for real." And then, oh,
thank you. You know, when when you're
laying in a when Thank you. when when
you're laying in a steel bunk in prison
surrounded by pedophiles, mafia dons,
and half of the Mexican cartels.
[laughter] You're laying there. I
remember laying there and asking God,
"Am I really that bad of of a person,
that I deserved this, that the entire
government takes a [__] on my head?"
Like, really, am I that bad? And then my
brother said to me, "I know you can't
possibly see this, but this is going to
turn out to be the best thing that ever
happened to you." And my my ex-wife, I'm
not supposed to talk about her by court
order, but I will say my ne my ex-wife
said, um, [snorts] well, at least you
don't have to hide your politics
anymore.
>> I hid my politics at the CIA for 15
years.
>> Yeah.
>> Second question.
>> [laughter]
[snorts]
>> That's a very good question. That's a
very good question. Well, I I'll give
you several answers. Number one, at the
CIA, they they teach us not to trust
anybody.
The guy that you sit next to for 10
years might be a Russian mole. You just
don't know. You hope he's not. He hopes
you're not.
[snorts] But don't trust anybody. I
allowed myself to trust one person.
And she's the one who betrayed me.
One. I'm not making that mistake again.
Number one. But what you're referring to
is true. I have said that the job of a
CIA case officer is to so ingratiate
yourself with a target that he comes to
like you love you so much he's willing
to commit espionage for you in some
cases treason. I I'll tell you it's
going to sound funny but it's not funny.
I developed this guy over the course of
a year and a half and we really hit it
off. In another life, in another world,
we really would be friends.
And he said to me one day, he said,
"You've been so kind to me and you've
been such a good friend
and you've never asked me for anything.
If there's something that I can ever do
for you, I want you to tell me." And I
said, 'Well, you could give me the plans
to that new Russian tank. [laughter]
I know you have it in your office and
I'd really like to see it,
[laughter]
but that's the job. I I There was one
guy that I recruited when when I was
leaving Greece. He cried when I left. He
cried.
So, somebody asked me recently on a
podcast
if I really was friends with any of the
people that I recruited. And I said,
"Oh, yeah. 90% of them. I love these
guys." And there have been a couple, and
we're not supposed to do this, but there
have been a couple where after I left
the CIA and I happened to be in their
country, I called them and we went out
to dinner.
>> Yeah. Not supposed to do that.
>> Yeah. That's not help. [sighs and gasps]
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. question over here. Oh, sorry.
Yeah, go ahead.
F
>> first of all, it's a pleasure.
>> Thank you.
>> Uh, I have certain views on this of my
own, but I'd like to to get your
perspective. Uh, where do you think the
relationship between Saudi Arabia and
the US stands today?
>> Uh, because there is a lot of
uncertainty.
>> Yes.
>> Uh, and where do you think it's going?
>> Oh, that's an important question. So
my very first overseas tour was in Saudi
Arabia. I started in Daiff with the
Kuwaiti ruling family. And then when
when we went back into Kuwait after
Kuwait the next summer I I finished in
Riyad.
If you go into the American embassy in
Riyad
in the main entrance, like you're going
to a meeting or something, you see a
photographic history of the relationship
from from Iban Sud all the way to, you
know, the current leadership with every
American president since the since
Franklin Roosevelt. And there are quotes
about what is called the special
relationship, right? We've always had
this special relationship with the
Saudis.
But then it was my experience that you
know what I I let me rephrase that.
It became my understanding confirmed to
me by two former US ambassadors to Saudi
Arabia with whom I'm still close
that the special relationship is just
lip service. We buy Saudi oil, the
Saudis buy American weapons and that's
it. We like each other because we kind
of have to. Um, it's a it's a very deep
relationship economically, but we don't
necessarily like each other. And I I'll
tell you just one personal anecdote. I
was so excited to go to Saudi Arabia the
first time. So, this was in 1990 in like
August of 1990. The Iraqis had just
invaded Kuwait. The Kuwaitis had run out
and uh had relocated to Tif. So there
was a um there was a guard at the back
of the American
we we called it we called it a base. It
was kind of a consulate and kind of a
temporary anyway. And I was so proud
that I had learned a little bit of
Arabic when I saw him the very first
day. I was going in for my very first
day of work and I saidam
and he ignored me. I thought huh that
was kind of rude but all right whatever.
So I go in I work my day. The next
morning I went in and I saidalamu
alaykum and he ignores me again. And I
thought I wonder what his problem is.
The third dayamkum
and he just looked at me and I stopped
and I said what's your problem?
And he said you are hired help.
[laughter] We paid for you to be here.
We paid for you to liberate Kuwait.
We're not friends.
And I thought, wow. Well, thanks for
laying it out for me. Um, Joe Biden went
too far by calling uh, Crown Prince
Muhammad bin Salman a murderer.
Even if he is a murderer, you don't say
it out loud. I mean, if you're the
president, you could have the Washington
Post say it in an op-ed, but you can't
say something like that. There's a
there's a bigger picture here, and the
bigger picture is the long-term
relationship.
Um, Donald Trump, to his credit, appears
to have repaired that relationship. But
when I was in the Gulf the other day,
every country I went to, they they
complained about, you know, all these
Trump people. They come here and they
want to talk about, you know, diplomacy
and and economic cooperation for a
minute
and then they try to get you to pay for
a hotel,
>> like to build the hotel, not to pay for
your room, to build the resort and just
give it to them.
He said they're crooked real estate
agents is what they are. And I think the
Saudis are tired of that. I think that
the Saudis have come to the realization
that you know what, it was good while it
lasted, but they don't really need the
United States so much anymore.
I think that's where we are.
>> Okay. Question on this side.
>> Yes,
>> please.
>> Um, so, uh, two comments. Hi, John.
>> Hi, Maria.
>> Maria from New York City. I I also left
the Democratic party and I feel almost
abandoned like a lot of people in
America. They went on some policies very
far right and on some policies
>> very
>> way far left like off the cliff.
>> Oh, there was this guy in my office who
came in address one day and I said, "You
look ridiculous."
>> Absolutely. It's delusion. It's
delusional and I don't have to
participate with that delusion. So,
second comments, John, and I don't want
anyone to get tri triggered because I
will say the teen name, I pray President
Trump pardons you.
>> Oh, thanks. So do I. We'll see.
>> And [laughter] um
>> thank you.
>> As a Greek American active in my church,
St. Nicholas at World Trade Center,
there is
>> wonderful
>> a Greek American who is very close with
President Trump. I won't say his name.
>> Oh, we've spoken a number of times.
>> Okay. He said, he said, "How is it that
we don't know each other?" I said,
"We've met three times and we've taken
pictures together." [laughter]
>> I just wanted to talk to you afterwards
with your permission to talk to him.
>> Thank you. That's a big yes. And I'm
going to call him when I get home.
>> Okay. So, I will talk to you afterwards
as well.
>> Thank you. I appreciate
>> you. Thank you.
>> Thanks very much.
We have a uh I think we're all the way
back there. Oh,
>> thank you very much. Um very delightful
insights as always.
>> I always enjoy your podcasts and uh all
the wisdom you share with the world.
>> Thank you.
>> Um my question has to do with the
specific uh strategic mix that has that
goes into the the tool case that the
intelligence community is using. I know
I am aware that you prioritize human
human intelligence above uh all of the
other aspects of intelligence but I
wanted to ask you what do you think
about the operational role of opensource
intelligence oint
>> ah yeah
>> as as of uh today
>> critically important
you know it's funny there's like a uh
there's a community bias
against OSENT in OSENT is open- source
intelligence press media. Um there's
this
bias against it
that that comes out of the bad old days
of you know reading TAS and Pravda or
reading every newspaper in India and
Pakistan and just getting variations of
you know hatred of one another. But for
many years, we underestimated the the
import of open- source um intelligence.
The Soviets didn't. The Soviets always
took it very very seriously. And they
developed something in the 1960s called
the mosaic concept. They said, 'If you
read every American newspaper and every
American scholarly journal, there's
going to be enough
important information at the
unclassified level that will allow you
to put together a mosaic of a classified
program. And that was true. There was a
uh you know the um who's the guy that
wrote Jack Ryan?
>> Um Tom
>> Tom Clancy. Thanks.
In 1991 when uh a year and a half after
I started at the agency, the agency
created a Tom Clansancy task force,
right? They said Tom Clansancy in his
book, The Hunt for Red October,
obviously had access to classified
information because he accurately
described the interior
the the the control room of a nuclear
submarine. and you have to be cleared at
the top secret level to even have access
to uh to the bridge in a nuclear
submarine.
No, he just read everything that those
guys published
and he was able to put it together and
so they had to disband the Tom Clansancy
task force. But yeah, OSENT is
critically important especially if you
want to get a a sense of of what the
public is thinking about an issue. If
you don't want the the government
position, you're you're already getting
the government position, you know, from
the State Department, you have to read
the press.
>> And I imagine with with social media
today, your your your OEN source is uh
is massive, right? I mean,
>> it's it's just exploded exponentially.
>> Yeah. Do we have time for one more?
Okay. Um perhaps this gentleman.
>> Sure.
I'm sorry we don't have time for more
questions.
>> Hi.
>> I wanted to ask, is there something that
scares you that you believe if it
happens is going to be the point of no
return with all these job politics going
around?
>> Yeah. I heard
I heard two weeks ago
from two people speaking independently
of one another
that Donald Trump is actively
considering the use of a tactical
nuclear weapon in Iran.
not because we need to use a tactical
nuclear weapon, but because he believes
that nuclear weapons are the final taboo
and he wants to break the taboo with a
small nuke so that future presidents can
feel free to use big nukes.
And the way I heard it, literally
everybody in the cabinet shouted that
that was the worst possible thing that
any president could do in the history of
the republic
and he backed off. Now,
there was a second report about a week
ago that
he asked General Kaine, the chairman of
the Joint Chiefs of Staff, uh, for the
nuclear codes. And General Kaine refused
to give him the nuclear nuclear codes.
General Kaine said that's not true. But
there were people who were in the room
at the time at a lower level saying no,
that was true.
So, we keep saying, you know,
now I'm not going to say what we keep
saying because I've applied for a pardon
and I'm hoping for the best, but we're
in very very dangerous times right now.
The most dangerous times in my lifetime.
I have I'm I'm just old enough that I I
barely have a memory of the summer of
1968.
Robert Kennedy was was well, Martin
Luther King was killed in April. Robert
Kennedy was was killed in uh in June and
then
gigantic
demonstrations began in some cases riots
against the Vietnam War. A year later
was the Kent State shooting.
And I remember it.
And then we went into this period where
we didn't have anything that was so
severe.
And now we're getting to a point where
we're getting ready to explode again.
like it's coming. Everybody sees it that
it's coming. But we're so divided as a
country that nobody feels that they have
the power to stop it.
It's It's going to get worse before it
gets any better. And worse is going to
mean people are going to die.
Yeah.
>> On that happy note,
>> yes.
[laughter]
No, I'd really like to thank you on
behalf of all of us for
>> Thank you
>> for really being honest.
>> Oh, it's so great to be in Cypus. Thank
you so much. Thank you. [applause]
[music]
>> Appreciate that.
>> It's just really really rare to hear an
honest uh open.
>> You know what? I have literally nothing
to lose. So I say whatever comes into my
mind. [laughter]
Thank you for listening [music] to
Cypress Diaspora Uncovered. Subscribe to
our podcast on Spotify or Apple Podcasts
for more inspiring conversations that
are [music] shaping Cypress's global
future. You can also explore more
episodes on our website and selected
video interviews on our YouTube
channels. [music]